Finding Aid for American Council on Alcohol Problems Records 1883-2015
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American Council on Alcohol Problems Records 1883-2015 1920s-1960s
American Council on Alcohol Problems.
Formerly the Anti-Saloon League of America. Correspondence, reports, minutes, legal files, speeches by temperance leaders, bills relating to the prohibition question; papers (1934-1956) concerning National Temperance and Prohibition Council; pamphlets relating to temperance; and photographs.
85650 Bj 2 UBJl
7 linear feet in 9 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group is comprised mainly of the records of the Office of General Counsel and Legislative Superintendent of the Anti-Saloon League of America. The records were deposited in the Michigan Historical Collections in February of 1969 by the Executive Director of the American Council on Alcohol Problems 4813, successor organization to the Anti-Saloon League.
The record group is open for research.
Those portions of this record group dated 1883-1933 were microfilmed in 1979 as part of a joint project of the Michigan Historical Collections, the Ohio Historical Society, and the Woman's Christian Temperance Union.
The Anti-Saloon League of America (A.S.L.A.), established in 1893, was a non-partisan political pressure organization which sought to mobilize church forces against the liquor traffic. One of the most important and most powerful components within the A.S.L.A. was the Office of General Counsel and Legislative Superintendent. The combined offices were charged with lobbying for favorable prohibition measures in Congress and arguing the legal cases which involved the A.S.L.A. Beyond these functionary activities, the Office of General Counsel and Legislative Superintendent, for nearly a decade, served as the leading force in shaping the philosophy and policy of the national A.S.L.A.
The importance of the Office of General Counsel and Legislative Superintendent (hereafter: Legal and Legislative office) resulted from the vigor and tenacity of one man, Wayne Bidwell Wheeler. Known to many as the "Dry Boss," Wheeler used the office to build a strong locus of power from which he impressed his personal philosophy upon the League and influenced national legislation. The dedication which Wheeler manifested from 1916 to 1927 was the culmination of a lifetime of hard work and opposition to the use of alcohol. Born in Brookfield, Ohio in November, 1869, Wheeler worked on his father's farm and attended Brookfield elementary schools. During his youth, he had been frightened by the effect of alcohol on one of his relatives and decided to dedicate his life to prohibition. After graduating from high school in Sharon, Pennsylvania in 1885, he planned to return to his father's farm and continue the family tradition. Wheeler was more interested in academics than agriculture, however, and soon left the farm to pursue advanced education. To save enough money for entrance fees, Wheeler taught in the Brookfield area for two years. He then entered Oberlin College in 1889. Throughout his student days, Wheeler worked at numerous odd jobs to pay tuition. As a center for the growing prohibition sentiment, Oberlin cemented Wheeler's skepticism about liquor. During his sophomore year, he came into contact with Howard Hyde Russell, the founder of the Anti-Saloon League. Impressed by Wheeler's intelligence, capacity for hard work and dedication to prohibition, Russell recruited him for the League. Despite his taxing college schedule, Wheeler began to tour Ohio for the League and also played a substantial role in promoting the first local option law in Ohio. After graduating from Oberlin with a Bachelor's degree in 1893 and a Master's degree in 1894, he accepted the post of superintendent of the League's Cleveland district and used the opportunity to attend the law school at Western Reserve University in Cleveland. Upon graduation from law school in 1898, he became attorney for the Ohio Anti-Saloon League. Three years later he married Ella B. Candy.
In 1903 Wheeler was elected Superintendent of the Ohio League. As Superintendent he continued the League's policy of supporting the dry candidates of the two major political parties and opposed pressure on the League to support the National Prohibition Party. In the 1905 Ohio gubernatorial election, the Ohio League helped to elect a dry Democrat over a wet Republican in the traditionally Republican state. Wheeler was successful in his local leadership role and emerged on the national scene when the A.S.L.A. intensified its campaign for national prohibition in 1913. He lobbied for the A.S.L.A. in the United States Congress, building strong relationships with senators and representatives which he later used to successfully promote wartime prohibition. Wheeler was appointed General Counsel of the A.S.L.A. in 1916 because of his successful career in Ohio and his growing reputation in Washington. From this position he was instrumental in securing the passage of the Eighteenth Amendment. In 1919 Wheeler also took the post of Legislative Superintendent. Combined, the two offices provided him a strong base of power within the A.S.L.A. His strength was enhanced by the fact that he not only enjoyed a good relationship with some members of Congress, but also had a close friendship with his fellow Ohioan, Warren G. Harding. Thus he exerted considerable pressure in the appointment of federal judges and other federal officials.
From 1920 to 1927, Wheeler exercised a powerful influence within the League and in both houses of Congress. One example of Wheeler's power within the A.S.L.A. came in 1924 when he personally secured the election of F. Scott McBride to the office of General Superintendent. In the early part of the 1920's the League split on the question of following an enforcement or educational policy. On one side, General Superintendent Purley A. Baker and his supporters called for a strong educational program to supplement legal prohibition. Baker's followers believed that only a favorable public atmosphere, created by educational programs, would ensure compliance to prohibition laws. On the other side, Wheeler and his followers stressed that strict law enforcement of prohibition and the Volstead Act would end the need for educational activity. Until his death in 1927, the Wheeler modus operandi dominated the A.S.L.A. Following the enforcement philosophy, Wheeler used his offices to launch a program of lobbying for stronger law enforcement measures in Congress to halt the illegal liquor traffic. He called for government agencies to be invested with greater power (such as more lenient search and seizure laws) in order to enforce the Eighteenth Amendment and the Volstead Act. He also successfully lobbied against attempts to make 2.75% beer legal and supported legislation to stop the production of fruit juices in American homes. In addition, Wheeler tried to curtail the use of liquor in the foreign embassies of Washington. In one of his most controversial stands, he committed the A.S.L.A. to supporting legislation that would limit the number of immigrants, believing that most immigrants tended to ignore the prohibition laws. Concerning the A.S.L.A. itself, Wheeler attempted to incorporate the League to relieve its tax burden.
Determined to control the League and to make his influence felt in national affairs, Wheeler drove himself almost fanatically throughout the period 1910 to 1927. Gradually, the hard driving pace began to take its toll. With his health deteriorating rapidly, Wheeler's problems increased when his wife was burned to death in a freak accident. Despite these adversities, poor health did not force him to limit his activities until the early summer of 1927. Wheeler died on September 5, 1927, at the age of 58.
With Wheeler's death, A.S.L.A. Superintendent McBride used the opportunity to shift power from Wheeler's office back to the Superintendent's office. To facilitate the return of power, McBride appointed the less dynamic Edward Bradstreet Dunford to fill the office of General Counsel and Legislative Superintendent. Dunford was born December, 1890 in Manchester, Virginia, and was raised by parents who favored prohibition. He attended Richmond College where he received a degree in law in 1915. Through his job as attorney for the Commissioner of Prohibition in Virginia, he received the financial security that enabled him to marry Laura Bear in 1917. As a competent attorney and a dedicated prohibitionist, Dunford caught Wheeler's eye. In 1920 Wheeler recruited him to serve as the assistant attorney in the Legal and Legislative Office. With seven years of training by the time of Wheeler's death, Dunford seemed a logical replacement as General Counsel and Legislative Superintendent. But unlike his predecessor, Dunford was a more cautious leader and never commanded the national prestige and power which Wheeler had enjoyed.
Throughout the 1920's the prohibition organizations were forced on the defensive. Following the passage of the Eighteenth Amendment, many strong advocates of prohibition were convinced that the battle was over. For most prohibitionists, repeal was inconceivable. As a result, financial contributions to the A.S.L.A. and other prohibition organizations declined precipitously. At the same time the A.S.L.A. was no longer able to attract the same caliber of outstanding leadership that had once marked the movement. For these reasons, after 1927, the League exerted less influence in the Congress, and by 1930 was forced to deal with a growing and powerful movement for repeal.
Unable to stem the widening public pressure for repeal, the League turned from the strong law enforcement tendencies of Wheeler to more restrained educational programs. Beginning in 1932, Dunford and other A.S.L.A. leaders fought their last major battle of the prohibition era. In an effort to stop the movement to repeal the 18th Amendment, they urged the government not to submit the issue to state constitutional conventions. Instead, A.S.L.A. leaders advocated the traditional procedure of having the proposed amendment voted on by state legislatures, where the League retained much greater influence. They lost this fight and the subsequent effort to stop repeal. Nevertheless, the A.S.L.A. continued in later years to work for effective prohibition laws.
The name of the organization was changed in 1950 to the National Temperance League, then in 1964 to the American Council on Alcohol Problems.
The records are primarily of the Office of General Counsel and Legislative Superintendent of the Anti-Saloon League of America (1883-1933). Additionally, there are later materials (1934-1969) of the organization following the repeal of the prohibition amendment. The record group consists of seven feet of correspondence, reports, speeches and legal files.
Subjects:
American Council on Alcohol Problems.; Lincoln-Lee Legion, Inc.; National Temperance and Prohibition Council.; Prohibition--United States.; Temperance--United States.
Subjects - Visual Material:
American Council on Alcohol Problems.; Prohibition--United States.; Temperance--United States.; Women.
Contributors:
Anti-Saloon League of America.; Anti-Saloon League of Michigan.; Cannon, James, 1864-1944.; Capper, Arthur, 1865-1951.; Cherrington, Ernest Hurst, 1877-1950.; Christgau, Oscar Gottlieb.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Dunford, Edward B. (Edward Bradstreet), 1890-1966; McBride, Francis Scott, 1872-1955.; Russell, Howard H. (Howard Hyde), 1855-1946.; Smoot, Reed, 1862-1941.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Vinson, Fred M., 1890-1953.; Volstead, Andrew John, 1860-1947.; Watson, James E., 1863-1948.; Wheeler, Wayne Bidwell, 1869-1927.
Genre/Form:
Cartoons.; Photographs.; Posters.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series deals with a wide variety of subjects, from efforts to incorporate the A.S.L.A. as a tax-free organization to specific legal points in prohibition laws. Although many letters contain only routine information, some letters from Congressmen explain their reasons for supporting or opposing prohibition legislation. Readers should note that it was the practice of this office to use the obverse of letters received as blank sheets for carbons of the reply. Hence correspondence is not in strict chronological order.
  Correspondence prior to ratification of the Eighteenth Amendment concerns Oklahoma's dry law, the 1917 Virginia gubernatorial campaign, and court cases involving prohibition issues. From 1921 to 1923, correspondents discussed the operation of the Volstead Act, problems of prohibition law enforcement, Abraham Lincoln's attitude toward prohibition, and various state prohibition laws. Major issues discussed in 1924 included Congressional appropriations for prohibition enforcement, constitutionality of the Volstead Act, the Cramton Bill designed to correct defects in the Prohibition Law Enforcement Bill (H.R.6645), proposals to legalize 2.75% beer, and other legal aspects of prohibition. These same issues were prominent in 1925, with lengthy debate on the additional question of whether the Anti-Saloon League should be incorporated as a tax-free organization.
  Most of the correspondence for 1926 is dated in December, when the Legal Office's attention was occupied by the Tumey v. State of Ohio case, which concerned what agency should receive fines obtained from prohibition law violations. The Legal Office sent letters to state superintendents regarding appropriation of prohibition fines in their states and received answers from almost every state attorney general. During 1927 important legal concerns of the Anti-Saloon League included whether the prohibition amendment should be changed from exclusion of "intoxicating" beverages to the broader category of "alcoholic" beverages; how to collect income tax from illegal bootleggers; prohibition in Puerto Rico; the Tumey v. Ohio case; and possible incorporation of the A.S.L.A. Several Senators and Congressmen wrote letters describing how much discussion there was over use of the word "intoxicating" when the prohibition amendment was debated in Congress.
  In 1928 the A.S.L.A. continued to consider incorporation of the League's Educational Foundation for tax purposes. Correspondence with the Internal Revenue Service examined the possibility that contributions to the Educational Foundation could be considered tax deductible because of the A.S.L.A.'s religious affiliations. The League also argued that the Senate should impeach Judge Cooper for his failure to enforce prohibition laws. Prohibition enforcement is the main theme in correspondence for 1929. Important topics include temperance education in public schools, funding needs of the government's prohibition department, failure of the Supreme Court to enforce prohibition laws, whether foreign diplomats should be prosecuted for prohibition violations, and the illegality of making wine and beer at home.
  Correspondence from 1930 to 1932 discussed the case of United States v. Sprague concerning constitutionality of the 18th Amendment; a bill to facilitate stricter control over fermented fruit juices; and incorporation of the A.S.L.A. There is also information about the January, 1932 A.S.L.A. convention; close relations between the A.S.L.A. and Senators Arthur Robinson and Morris Sheppard; and Republican and Democratic platform planks advocating legalization of 2.75% beer. Following the November, 1932 election, fear of Prohibition repeal culminated in A.S.L.A. cooperation with the W.C.T.U. in sponsoring a "Resist Repeal" convention in Washington, D.C., December 9-11.
  Correspondence for January-June, 1933 deals largely with the fight against the 21st Amendment, including charges that it was unconstitutional, discussion of methods to prevent repeal, and attacks on state ratification convention procedures. There was still some interest in incorporation of the League, possibly due to continuing financial difficulties. From July to December, correspondence focuses on the repeal movement, particularly the alleged unconstitutionality of repeal conventions and charges of fraud in elections to the conventions. The A.S.L.A. at first had tried to stop the entire repeal process, but then attempted to win the elections in order to defeat ratification. Correspondence indicates that the League concentrated its efforts in Missouri, Maine, Arizona and Ohio.
  - Undated 1917-1969, 31 folders (Box 1)
- Reports and Minutes
  The Reports and Minutes contain substantive documents on important aspects of the Legal and Legislative Office. These papers clearly demonstrate the issues which the League deemed the most important, such as the best method for electing dry delegates to the state conventions and the conclusions from experiments on the effects of 2.75% beer.
  There are seven folder of undated Reports and Minutes. Within the first undated folder are memorandum of a legal brief concerning the constitutional validity of the 18th Amendment; information concerning the Webb-Kenyon Bill; efforts to increase government control of medicinal liquors; statements favorable to prohibition by presidents from James Madison to Andrew Johnson; and a "Summary of the Provisions of the Proposed Prohibition Enforcement Act" for the District of Columbia. The second undated folder includes a report on the 18th Amendment and its relation to the Constitution, which provides a synopsis of arguments for prohibition, disputes certain "fictions" about alcohol, and discusses future prospects for prohibition; a sermon written by William Jennings Bryan; information on the Supplemental Prohibition Enforcement Act, including how Congressmen voted on the bill; and requests to the government for clarification or rulings on such issues as unlawful possession of liquor and alcohol as the object of larceny.
  The third undated folder contains information on A.S.L.A. legislative policy; a list of Wayne Wheeler's important legal cases, particularly those involving prohibition; discussion of A.S.L.A. support for the 16th Amendment, adopted in 1913, which provided for a Federal income tax; an article debating the constitutionality of the Jenks Bill, concerning local versus federal authority over prohibition; Wheeler's evaluation of enforcement of the 18th Amendment, particularly the prohibition codes; a report on manufacture and sale of intoxicating liquor containing 2.75% or less alcohol, under regulation of the Wartime Prohibition Act; and information on Congressional and legal case attempts to define the word "intoxicating."
  The fourth undated folder contains information about supplemental prohibition bills, Lincoln's prohibition views, state enforcement of the 18th Amendment, state efforts to modify or evade prohibition regulations, concurrent power and the supremacy of Federal law, applicability of the 18th Amendment to Puerto Rico, and whether brewers should be compensated for confiscated liquor. The fifth undated folder contains an A.S.L.A. convention manual; an American Bar Association statement; information concerning a bill to create an Alcoholic Liquor Damage and Indemnity Fund; and literature concerning attempts to pass previous Constitutional amendments.
  The last two undated folders include information concerning: legality of constitutional amendment conventions; definitions of "intoxicating liquors" in state statutes adopted prior to the 18th Amendment; the constitutionality of Section 29 of the Prohibition Amendment, dealing with fruit juices and cider; various state tests for drunken driving; the record of Supreme Court Justice Brandeis, whom the A.S.L.A. severely criticized; and a list of dry Congressmen in the 69th Congress (1925-1927).
  Reports and Minutes for 1912-1919 include the Post Office Department's "Liquor Bulletin No. 2" concerning regulations against liquor advertising, an article on "The Statewide Initiative and Referendum" statutes, a copy of The Ohio Law Reporter, and information concerning: A.S.L.A. Legislative Committee chairman James Cannon's protests against appointment of Louis Brandeis and William Howard Taft to the Supreme Court, due to their pro-liquor stances; the Reed Amendment to outlaw liquor advertising in the mail; and League involvement in a contested election in Pennsylvania.
  Reports and Minutes for 1920-1922 include information concerning: concurrent powers, whether a state legislature can nullify Congressional laws, liquor prosecutions in Federal courts, demands for more efficient enforcement and prosecution of prohibition violators, whether beer should be used as a medicine; and applicability of the 18th Amendment to vessels on the high seas. Material from 1923 deals with such topics as: the Supreme Court's Constitutional role; the President's law enforcement responsibilities; collecting funds for the A.S.L.A. at Sunday church services; requests for New York Governor Al Smith to enforce the 18th Amendment; arguments against repeal of New York's Mulligan-Gage inspection law; and income tax provisions for contributions to the A.S.L.A. This folder also contains a copy of the A.S.L.A. constitution.
  Reports and Minutes for 1924 includes information concerning: whether a state can license the sale of 2.5% beer; definitions of the term "intoxicating liquor"; the President's power to pardon those convicted of violating the Volstead Act; a proposed treaty with Britain to stop liquor smuggling; and the Cramton Bill to establish a Bureau of Prohibition under the Treasury Department. Material on the Cramton Bill includes a legal brief, a booklet on hearings before the House Judiciary Committee, and proposed amendments to the bill.
  Reports and Minutes for 1925-1927 contains information concerning: various legal problems; industrial alcohol and 2.75% beer; the Couzens Bill; a reorganization bill to create a prohibition department within the executive branch of government; prohibition enforcement authority; applicability of income tax laws to the illegal liquor traffic, and "wet" plans to repeal the 18th Amendment through another constitutional amendment.
  Material for 1928-1929 includes: an A.S.L.A. Legal Office report on the 1928 Presidential election; judicial decisions on Congressional authority to endow U.S. Commissioners with power to hear and decide misdemeanor cases; a Legal Office report to the A.S.L.A. Executive Committee concerning regulations and by-laws of the Educational Foundation which relate to its incorporation; proposals to increase penalties under the National Prohibition Act; prohibition resolutions introduced in Congress; copies of state scientific temperance laws; a report on the California grape industry; and a summary of state laws relating to traffic in intoxicating liquors.
  Reports and Minutes for 1930 include literature on national constitutional conventions; a response to a New Jersey judge's charge that the 18th Amendment was invalid; clippings and a legal brief on upholding the 18th Amendment; arguments for government control of medicinal spirits and editorials on the Sheppard Bill for prohibition enforcement in Washington, D.C. There are also prohibition surveys of Virginia, Florida, Kentucky and Georgia--including information on legislation, the judiciary, enforcement personnel, public officials' attitudes toward prohibition, and death rates from alcoholism and cirrhosis of the liver.